Guide to the Nadine Eckhardt Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Nadine Eckhardt Papers
1920-2009
1944-2009
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Eckhardt, Nadine, 1931-
SWWC.105
6 Linear Feet
14 boxes
Correspondence, photographs, personal papers, and other research materials represent the life of Nadine Eckhardt, author of Duchess of Palms. The materials were collected over the life span of Eckhardt, born in 1931, and were used in research for her memoir. The materials are arranged into five series: Personal Papers, Correspondence, Photographs, Printed Materials and Dutches of Palms.
Scope and Contents
The Nadine Eckhardt Collection spans from the 1920s-2009. The collection is comprised of photographs, correspondence, business materials, newspapers clippings and early and final versions of Duchess of Palms. The original order of the Nadine Eckhardt Collection was maintained with minimal changes. The collection was originally arranged chronologically by Duchess of Palms materials, correspondence between Nadine and Billy Lee Brammer 1956-1968, correspondence between Bob, Nadine, and her family 1970s-1983, and Nadine's personal correspondence, 1944 through 1999. The chronological order was maintained, but the materials were organized into five series: Personal Papers - restaurant and scrapbook materials, Family Papers - Billy Lee Brammer, Bob Eckhardt, family, and personal, Photographs - organized chronologically, Print Materials - newspapers and other articles, and Duchess of Palms Materials - drafts, timelines and notes.
Original folder tiles are in quotation marks.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nadine Eckhardt, 2010.
Related Materials
For additional Billy Lee Brammer material, see the Billy Lee Brammer Papers (Collection 007).
Additional Bob Eckhardt papers can be found at the Briscoe Center for American History at the University of Texas at Austin.
Biographical Notes
Nadine Ellen Cannon was born in McAllen, Texas on January 20, 1931. After graduating from high school in 1948, Eckhardt enrolled in North Texas State College in Denton, Texas to pursue a Bachelor of Arts degree. While there she met her first husband, writer Billy Lee Brammer, whom she married in 1950 when she was nineteen years old. In 1951, she and Brammer moved to Austin where she worked for the University of Texas and briefly at the Austin American-Statesman newspaper. Two daughters, Sidney and Shelby, were born during this time. After several years in Austin, she and Brammer moved to Washington D.C. in 1955 to work on the staff of Texas Senator Lyndon B. Johnson. The marriage to Brammer began to deteriorate, and she moved back to Austin pregnant with their third child, William. The couple eventually divorced in 1961. During this time, Brammer released his critically acclaimed, but controversial book, The Gay Place, a fictional account of Texas politics.
Now single and working at the State Capitol, Nadine met Robert "Bob" Eckhardt, a Texas state representative from Houston, whom she married in 1962. The couple moved to Houston, Eckhardt's hometown, and the birthplace of their only child, daughter Sarah. In 1966, Bob Eckhardt ran for Congress. Eckhardt won, and Nadine moved to Washington, D.C. There she performed the duties of a congressman's wife as well as helping to manage Eckhardt's congressional staff. She became involved in women's rights issues and the Civil Rights movement of Dr. Martin Luther King. The Eckhardts separated in 1976 and divorced in 1977. Nadine moved back to Austin, Texas. After her divorce from Bob Eckhardt, Nadine opened a restaurant in east Austin – Nadine's, and she ran it for a year and a half.She moved to New York City and worked for another restaurant, also named Nadine's, owned by her daughter Sarah's boyfriend. In 1991, Nadine moved back to Austin permanently. While living in Austin, Eckhardt worked as an assistant to writer Molly Ivins, in real estate, and worked on Ann Richards' gubernatorial campaign in 1992. In 2009, Eckhardt released, Duchess of Palms, a memoir of her life and work in Washington D.C. and Austin, Texas. The title was inspired by a beauty pageant she had won as a teenager.
Eckhardt passed away on December 8, 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Autobiography; Political campaigns -- United States; Women authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Authors' spouses -- Texas; Politicians' spouses
Subjects (Persons)
Eckhardt, Nadine, 1931-; Eckhardt, Bob; Brammer, Billy Lee
- Personal Papers, 1950-2008
  Series Description
  The first series includes papers related to the life of Nadine Eckhardt. There are invitations for Bob and Nadine Eckhardt, drawings by unidentified sources, and documents relating to the restaurant Nadine's
  - "Bob Eckhardt list of invites" (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Drawings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Grandma" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Nadine's Restaurant" (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1944-2008
  The second series is divided into four subseries: Billy Lee Brammer, Bob Eckhardt, Family, and Other/Unidentified. All correspondence is arranged chronologically within the subseries. Included are many letters that Nadine Eckhardt wrote to others and photocopied for her own records. The largest of the subseries is Other/Unidentified, and within this contains correspondence with acclaimed journalist, Bob Sherrill and several of Eckhardt's high school boyfriends.
  - Billy Lee Brammer, 1951-1970
    - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bob Eckhardt, 1961-1987
    - 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Family, 1956-2006
    - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Other/Unidentified, 1944-2008, undated
    - 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1974 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1983 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1984 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1985 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1996 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1997 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1998 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 2003 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 2005 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 2006 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 2008 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Photographs, circa 1920-2009
  The photographs are arranged in chronological order by decade. Many of the earlier photographs include her mother and stepfather. There are some photographs of Nadine Eckhardt during the time she modeled. There are also numerous photographs of Nadine Eckhardt's children, Shelby, Sidney and Sarah, and many of Bob Eckhardt.
  - 1920-1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Contents
    Nadine Ellen Thompson (Nadine Eckhardt's mother)(photocopy)
    Leslie Wells (Nadine Eckhardt's biological father)(photocopy)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Noah Cannon, Nadine Cannon, Little Nadine, Leslie Cannon; circa 1939 taken by Denson Photo in Dallas, TX (photocopy)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Noah Lee Cannon (Nadine Eckhardt's adoptive father); circa mid 1940s (photocopy)
    Photo information sheet
  - 1950-1959 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    "Nadine Cannon modeling underwear and pjs for a Vanity Fair Factory near Denton, TX;"1949 or 1950 (photocopy)
    Photo information sheet for 1
    Nadine Cannon; 1949 or 1950(photocopy)
    Photo Information Sheet for 3
    Five "Children's Photos," 1950s
    Sam Rayburn and Ralph Yarborough; early 1950 (photocopy)
    "Nadine on roof of architecture building" 1951(photocopy)
    "Stevenson at press conference LBJ Ranch;" Grace Tully, Sam Rayburn, Lyndon Baines Johnson, Adlai; 1955 (photocopy)
    "Mary Margaret and Nadine sitting on Harry McPherson's knees at Party at Duggers House;" Mary Margaret Wylie, Harry McPherson and Nadine; 1955 (photocopy)
    "Nadine sitting on Harry McPherson's lap; 1955 (photocopy)
    "LBJ in majority leader's office; Lyndon Baines Johnson; 1955 or 1956(photocopy) "Nadine in Arlington House"taken by Bill Brammer (photocopy)
    "Willie Morris, Nadine Brammer with daughters Sydney and Shelby Brammer 1957 in front of house on Enfied Rd. Austin" 1957 (photocopy)
    "Nadine holding up fish at LBJ Ranch-with daughter Sidney" 1957 or 1958, taken by Bill Brammer (photocopy) Three photocopies taped onto one page
    "Nadine on NTSC campus. Taken by Bill Brammer 1950" taken by Bill Brammer (photocopy)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    "Nadine and Michael Janeway at Paleface Ranch" circa 1960 (3-1 photocopy) "Bob Eckhardt, State Representative from Houston" 1962 or 1963 photograph; taken by Russell Lee (2- both photocopies)
    Photo information sheet for 4 and 5 "Bob and Nadine 1963 moved into house newly built"
    "Bob and Nadine 1963 moved into house" Nadine and Bob Eckhardt "Russell Lee volunteered to take Bob's photo for his campaign for
    Congress in 1966"(photocopy)
    Photo Information Sheet for 9
    "L-R, Norma Eckhardt, Bob's mother, state rep. Bob Eckhardt who was running for Congress and Nadine Eckhardt, in Bob's Campaign HDQTRS. In 1966" 1966 (photocopy)
    "Congressman Bob Eckhardt and Nadine on Air Force One en route to Party in Austin with LBJ in June 16, 1967" (photocopy)
    "Bob Eckhardt, Bob Pierpoint (Newsman, deceased), Barbara Bush, Nadine, Jessica Hobby Cato, Cong. George Bush, Bill Hobby on Capitol Steps 1967" (photocopy)
    "Photo: L-R Paul (deceased), LBJ, Nadine, Bob Eckhardt, Bayou Club, Houston, at party in honor of John Connally 1969 Feb. 13" (photocopy)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    "Taken in District?;" Sarah Eckhardt (8 yrs old); April 30, 1973
    "Nadine, Bob and Sarah at reception in Bob's District Office for federal employees" April 30, 1973 (photocopy)
    "L-R Unknown, Unknown, Nadine, Beulah Shepard,1973"(photocopy)
    "L-R: Grace Tully, Nadine, State Senator Walter Richter, Nadine, Bob Eckhardt, Cong. Chick Kazen, at Andrews AFB, waiting for LBJs body to arrive" 1973 (3)
    "Hofneinz Pavilion in Houston, Mack Hofheinz was Mayor's wife;" 1974 (2- both photocopies)
    "Photos of Nadine, Betty Dooley and Ann Brinkley and Bob in front of house in Georgetown 1975" (photocopy)
    "1975" (33) "1976" (12) "1977" (5) "1979" (7)
  - 1978 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    "from 1978" (55)
    "from 1978" Duplicates of photos taken in Nadine's Restaurant (43)
    "from 1978" Funerals (9)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    "1970s photos" (38)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    "1980s" (9)
    "1981s" (23)
    "1981" "Photo of Nadine and Ann Richards Fundraiser at Nadine's in NYC October 30, 1989"
    "1981" "Nadine's in NYC 1988 or '89" (3)
  - "Nadine/Personal/Photos", 2006 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "Additional Scrapbook Materials" (10 family photos), undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Pics of Texas Capital by Rosalind Eckhardt plus photos of Bob", 1970-1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    "Roy and Lil at Ann Richards political Party - 9 Dec 1975"
    "Texas Capital by Rosalind Eckhardt in mid 70s" (19)
    Unidentified photos (14)
  - Miscellaneous, 1967-1989, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
    "George Crane 1971 Georgetown University Student"
    "G.W. Bush at dedication of LBJ Library, Austin 1967, taken by Eckhardt
    "Curtis Graves 68 and 89"(3)
    NASA Manned Spacecraft Center, Houston, TX; L-R Mrs. Robert Turner, Robert Tuner, Mrs. Bob Eckhardt, Astronaut Michael Collins; January 27, 1967 (3)
- Printed Material, 1955-2008
  The fourth series mainly consists of news clippings and magazine articles. These are arranged into subseries: Billy Lee Brammer, Bob Eckhardt, Nadine Eckhardt, Family, and related resources. There are documents, event programs, and articles related to travel included.
  - Articles, Billy Lee Brammer (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Articles, Bob Eckhardt (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Articles, Nadine (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Articles, Related Resources (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Documents (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Articles, Event Programs (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Articles, Travels (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Duchess of Palms, 1970-2009
  The fifth series is related to Eckhardt's research, writing, and publishing of her memoir Duchess of Palms. It includes timelines of Eckhardt's life and several working copies of the manuscript.
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Donegan, Craig (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Harpers & Row Publishers (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Texas Monthly Press (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - University of Texas Press (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Copyrights (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Timelines
    - "Summaries on timelines by year" (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - "BLB, Late fifties and early sixties" (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "1961-66" (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1966-1977" (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - "Written in 1976 by BLB and Nadine" (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - "1977-1988" (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - "1988-1989" (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Notes
    - "Transcripts of Interviews" (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Chronology of 55, 56, 57 Furnished by LBJ Library" (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "List of possible readers to read manuscript" (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Used while ending my book, brainstormed, 10-28-04" (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "Suggested titles" (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "Articles Re: What publishers are looking for" (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "The 60's" (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - "Articles about women to read for ideas" (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - "50's notes I used in chap.1" (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - "Writing styles/suggestions" (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "To myself, 1989, 87, 88" (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - "To myself 1982, 83, 90's" (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - "Scrapbook material 40's, 50's, 60's" (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - "Re 1973" (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - "On the 90's and earlier (70's, 60's)" (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - "End of book and epilogue" (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "Epilogue" (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Drafts
    - "Early Manuscripts" (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "7-16-07, with revisions sent to Allison Faust" (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Notes and revisions" (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "Includes schedule as of 3/12" (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "Copy of M.S. sent to Tim and Library of Congress" (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "Craig Donegan's efforts" (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - "Mother, Grandma, family" (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - "LBJ" (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - "Removed from Binder" (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - "M.S.S." (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - "Printed 6/16/05" (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - "Selected chapters with notes from Tim" (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - "Cleaned up M.S. 8-2-07 by KMJ" (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "Cleaned up M.S. 8-16-07 by KMJ" (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "Cleaned up MS 8-16-07" (Box 14, Folder 5)